<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
© 2016–2018 Jeremy Sylvestre

Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or
any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled “GNU Free
Documentation License” that appears in the output document of this
PreTeXt source code. All trademarks™ are the registered® marks of their
respective owners.
*********************************************************************-->


<section xml:id="section-special-forms-activities">

<title>Activities</title>

<introduction><p>
  Recall that the <term>main diagonal</term><idx><h>main diagonal</h></idx> of a square matrix refers to the entries on the diagonal from top left to bottom right. Here are some special types of <em>square</em> matrices for consideration.
  <dl>
    <li>
    <title><term>scalar matrix</term></title>
    <idx><h>scalar</h><h>matrix</h></idx>
    <idx><h>matrix</h><h>scalar</h></idx>
    <p>a scalar multiple of the identity matrix</p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <title><term>diagonal matrix</term></title>
    <idx><h>diagonal matrix</h></idx>
    <idx><h>matix</h><h>diagonal</h></idx>
    <p>all entries <em>not</em> on the main diagonal are zero</p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <title><term>upper triangular matrix</term></title>
    <idx><h>upper triangular matrix</h></idx>
    <idx><h>matix</h><h>upper triangular</h></idx>
    <p>all entries <em>below</em> the main diagonal are zero</p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <title><term>lower triangular matrix</term></title>
    <idx><h>lower triangular matrix</h></idx>
    <idx><h>matix</h><h>lower triangular</h></idx>
    <p>all entries <em>above</em> the main diagonal are zero</p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <title><term>symmetric matrix</term></title>
    <idx><h>symmetric matrix</h></idx>
    <idx><h>matix</h><h>symmetric</h></idx>
    <p>a matrix that is equal to its own transpose</p>
    </li>
  </dl>
</p></introduction>

<activity xml:id="activity-special-forms-exploring">
  <introduction>
    <p>
      Carry out the following tasks for <em>each</em> of the special types of matrices defined above. Think in general, and consider <em>every</em> possible size of matrix, not just <m>2\times 2</m> and <m>3\times 3</m>! You don't need to <em>prove</em> each answer, but you should be able to articulate an informal justification for each answer that doesn't rely on examples (unless it's a <em>counter</em>example).
    </p>
    <aside><title>Tip</title><p>
      When considering the questions in this activity for <em>symmetric</em> matrices, rather than trying to figure things out with examples, it is much easier to work algebraically with a letter <m>A</m> representing an arbitrary symmetric matrix, and use the definition of symmetric: <m>\utrans{A} = A</m>.
    </p></aside>
  </introduction>
  <!-- TODO overlapping asides....? -->
  <task><p>
    Write down both a <m>2\times 2</m> and a <m>3\times 3</m> example of the type.
		Is it clear why this type of matrix has been given its particular name?
  </p></task>
  <task><p>
    Does the (square) zero matrix have this type?
		Does an identity matrix?
		Does every <m>1\times 1</m>?
  </p></task>
  <task><p>
    If <m>A</m> is a matrix of this type, is every scalar multiple of <m>A</m> also of this type?
		Is <m>\utrans{A}</m> of this type?
  </p></task>
  <task><p>
    If <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> are matrices of this type and of the same size, is their sum of this type?
    Their product? A power (with a positive exponent)?
  </p></task>
  <task xml:id="activity-special-forms-exploring-invertible-criterion">
		<p><em>[Omit this task for symmetric matrices.]</em></p>
    <p>
    Recall that a matrix is invertible if and only if its RREF is the identity matrix. Based on this, can you come up with a simple condition by which you can determine whether a matrix of this type is invertible or not?
    </p>
  </task>
  <task xml:id="activity-special-forms-exploring-inverse">
    <p> If <m>A</m> is an invertible matrix of this type, is its inverse also of this type? </p>
    <aside><title>Note</title><p>
      For the case of symmetric matrices in <xref ref="activity-special-forms-exploring-inverse">Activity</xref>, it will be too complicated to work by examples. Instead, consider the formula <m>\utrans{(\inv{A})} = \inv{(\utrans{A})}</m> from <xref ref="proposition-inverses-transpose" /> and the definition of <term>symmetric matrix</term> above.
    </p></aside>
  </task>
  <task xml:id="activity-special-forms-exploring-ij-entries">
		<p> Come up with a condition or set of conditions on the entries <m>a_{ij}</m> of a square matrix <m>A</m> by which you can determine whether or not <m>A</m> is of this type. </p>
    <aside><title>Example</title><p>
      Here is an example of the type of condition we're looking for in
      <xref ref="activity-special-forms-exploring-ij-entries">Activity</xref>,
      in the case of the identity matrix: a square matrix <m>A</m> is equal to the identity matrix if <m>a_{ii} = 1</m> for all indices <m>i</m>, and <m>a_{ij} = 0</m> for all pairs of indices <m>i,j</m> with <m>i\neq j</m>.
    </p></aside>
  </task>

</activity>

<activity xml:id="activity-special-forms-diag-times">
  <introduction><p>
    Consider matrices
    <md><mrow>
      D \amp = \begin{bmatrix}2 \amp 0 \amp 0\\0 \amp 3 \amp 0\\0 \amp 0 \amp 5\end{bmatrix},
      \amp
      A \amp = \left[\begin{array}{rrr}
        1 \amp 1 \amp 1 \\
        -1 \amp -1 \amp -1 \\
        1 \amp 1 \amp 1
      \end{array}\right].
    </mrow></md>
  </p></introduction>
  <task><p>
		Compute <m>DA</m>. <em>Describe the pattern:</em> multiplying a matrix on the <em>left</em> by a diagonal matrix is the same as <fillin characters="20" />.
  </p></task>
  <task><p>
		Compute <m>AD</m>. <em>Describe the pattern:</em> multiplying a matrix on the <em>right</em> by a diagonal matrix is the same as <fillin characters="20" />.
  </p></task>
</activity>

<activity xml:id="activity-special-forms-upper-tri-decomp">
  <introduction><p>
    Consider the upper triangular matrix
    <me> U = \begin{bmatrix} 2 \amp 1 \amp 1 \\ 0 \amp 3 \amp 1 \\ 0 \amp 0 \amp 5 \end{bmatrix}. </me>
  </p></introduction>
  <task><p>
		Can you decompose <m>U</m> into a sum <m>U=D+P</m> of a diagonal matrix <m>D</m> and a <q>purely</q> upper triangular matrix <m>P</m>?
  </p></task>
  <task><p>
		Can you decompose <m>U</m> into a product <m>U=DR</m> of a diagonal matrix <m>D</m> and an upper triangular matrix <m>R</m> in REF?
  </p></task>
</activity>

<activity xml:id="activity-special-forms-nilp-powers">
  <introduction><p>
    Consider the upper triangular matrix
    <me>
      N = \begin{bmatrix}
        0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
        0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \\
        0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \\
        0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0
      \end{bmatrix}.
    </me>
  </p></introduction>
  <task><p>
    Compute <m>N^2</m>, <m>N^3</m>, and <m>N^4</m>. Do you notice a pattern?
  </p></task>
  <task><p> Without computing, what is <m>N^5</m>? <m>N^{99}</m>? </p></task>
  <task><p>
  	Make a conjecture (<ie /> a guess based on previous examples) about what will happen if you compute powers of a <m>5\times 5</m> matrix of a similar form, with all entries equal to <m>0</m> except for a line of <m>1</m>s down the first <q>superdiagonal.</q>
  </p></task>
</activity>

<activity xml:id="activity-special-forms-prove-sum-diagonal">
  <introduction>
    <p>
    This activity will guide you through proving that the sum of two diagonal matrices is again diagonal.
    </p><p>
  	Suppose that <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> are diagonal matrices of the same size. (But do <em>not</em> assume that they have a particular size like <m>2\times 2</m> or <m>3\times 3</m> or <etc />)
    </p>
  </introduction>
  <task xml:id="activity-special-forms-prove-sum-diagonal-setup"><p>
		Describe what our assumption that <m>A</m> is diagonal means about the entries of <m>A</m> in terms of your answer to
    <xref ref="activity-special-forms-exploring-ij-entries">Activity</xref>.
    Then do the same for <m>B</m>.
  </p></task>
  <task><p>
    Decide exactly what you need to check in order to be sure that the sum <m>A+B</m> is diagonal, in terms of your answer to
    <xref ref="activity-special-forms-exploring-ij-entries">Activity</xref>.
    Then carry out that check, using your answer to
    <xref ref="activity-special-forms-prove-sum-diagonal-setup" text="type-hybrid" />.
  </p></task>
</activity>

<activity xml:id="activity-special-forms-prove-sum-symmetric">
  <introduction>
    <p>
    This activity will guide you through proving that the sum of two symmetric matrices is again symmetric. Unlike the proof in <xref ref="activity-special-forms-prove-sum-diagonal" />, we will not need to consider individual entries, since the definition of <term>symmetric matrix</term> does not refer to individual entries like the definition of <term>diagonal matrix</term> does.
    </p><p>
  	Suppose that <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> are symmetric matrices of the same size. (But do <em>not</em> assume that they have a particular size like <m>2\times 2</m> or <m>3\times 3</m> or <etc />)
    </p>
  </introduction>
  <task xml:id="activity-special-forms-prove-sum-symmetric-setup"><p>
		Express what it means for <m>A</m> to be symmetric in mathematical notation, using the symbols <m>A</m>, <m>\utrans{}</m>, and <m>=</m>. Then do the same for <m>B</m>.
  </p></task>
  <task xml:id="activity-special-forms-prove-sum-symmetric-what-to-check"><p>
		Express what it would mean for the sum <m>A+B</m> to be symmetric in mathematical notation, similarly to
    <xref ref="activity-special-forms-prove-sum-symmetric-setup" text="type-hybrid" />.
  </p></task>
  <task><p>
    Your expressions from
    <xref ref="activity-special-forms-prove-sum-symmetric-setup" text="type-hybrid" />
    are <em>things we are assuming to be true</em>. Your expression from
    <xref ref="activity-special-forms-prove-sum-symmetric-what-to-check" text="type-hybrid" />
    is <em>the condition that needs to be verified</em>. Carry out this verification, <em>making sure to use proper LHS vs RHS procedure</em>. In this verification, you will need to use your assumed knowledge from
    <xref ref="activity-special-forms-prove-sum-symmetric-setup" text="type-hybrid" />
    as well as an algebra rule from <xref ref="proposition-matrix-ops-algebra-rules" />.
  </p></task>
</activity>

</section>
