<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
© 2016–2018 Jeremy Sylvestre

Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or
any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled “GNU Free
Documentation License” that appears in the output document of this
PreTeXt source code. All trademarks™ are the registered® marks of their
respective owners.
*********************************************************************-->


<section xml:id="section-subspaces-theory">

<title>Theory</title>

<assemblage><title>In this section</title><p><ul>
<li><xref ref="subsection-subspaces-theory-test" /><nbsp /><nbsp />
<em><xref text="title" ref="subsection-subspaces-theory-test" /></em></li>
<li><xref ref="subsection-subspaces-theory-examples" /><nbsp /><nbsp />
<em><xref text="title" ref="subsection-subspaces-theory-examples" /></em></li>
<li><xref ref="subsection-subspaces-theory-equality" /><nbsp /><nbsp />
<em><xref text="title" ref="subsection-subspaces-theory-equality" /></em></li>
</ul></p></assemblage>

<subsection xml:id="subsection-subspaces-theory-test">
<title>The Subspace Test</title>

<p> First we formally state the Subspace Test, and provide a proof. </p>

<proposition xml:id="proposition-subspaces-test">

	<title>The Subspace Test</title><idx><h>Subspace Test</h></idx><idx><h>subspace</h><h>test</h></idx>

	<statment><p>
	A subcollection of vectors in a vector space is a subspace if and only if all three of the following conditions are met.
	<ol label="(i)">
		<li xml:id="proposition-subspaces-test-nonempty">
		The subcollection is nonempty. That is, it contains at least one vector.
		</li>
		<li xml:id="proposition-subspaces-test-add-closed">
		The subcollection is <em>closed</em> under vector addition. That is, given vectors <m>\uvec{w}_1</m> and <m>\uvec{w}_2</m> in the subcollection, the sum <m>\uvec{w}_1+\uvec{w}_2</m> is also in the subcollection.
		</li>
		<li xml:id="proposition-subspaces-test-smul-closed">
		The subcollection is <em>closed</em> under scalar multiplication. That is, given vector <m>\uvec{w}</m> in the subcollection and scalar <m>k</m>, the scaled vector <m>k\uvec{w}</m> is also in the subcollection.
		</li>
	</ol>
	</p></statment>

	<proof><p>
	Suppose we have a subcollection of vectors in a vector space that satisfies the three conditions of the Subspace Test. We would like to verify that this subcollection is a vector space all on its own, using the same vector addition and scalar multiplication operations as the larger space. But as explored in
	<xref ref="activity-subspaces-subspace-test-precursor" />
	and discussed in
	<xref ref="subsection-subspaces-concepts-recognizing" />,
	we don't need to verify all ten vector space axioms <mdash /> we get the six algebra axioms for free from knowing that is how vector algebra works in the larger space. The remaining four axioms are
	<xref ref="list-abstract-vec-spaces-concepts-add-axioms-closed" text="local">Axiom A</xref>,
	<xref ref="list-abstract-vec-spaces-concepts-add-axioms-zero" text="local">Axiom A</xref>,
	<xref ref="list-abstract-vec-spaces-concepts-add-axioms-neg" text="local">Axiom A</xref>,
	and
	<xref ref="list-abstract-vec-spaces-concepts-smul-axioms-closed" text="local">Axiom S</xref>,
	so we really only need to verify that the subcollection contains the zero vector, and is closed under vector addition, scalar multiplication, and taking negatives. Furthermore, from
	<xref ref="proposition-subspaces-test-add-closed">Condition</xref>
	and
	<xref ref="proposition-subspaces-test-smul-closed">Condition</xref>
	of the test, we already know that the subcollection is closed under addition and scalar multiplication. So we are down to checking the zero vector and negatives.
	</p><p>
	To show that the subcollection must contain the zero vector, consider that
	<xref ref="proposition-subspaces-test-nonempty">Condition</xref>
	of the test guarantees that the subcollection contains <em>some</em> vector <m>\uvec{v}</m>. But then
	<xref ref="proposition-subspaces-test-smul-closed">Condition</xref>
	of the test tells us that the subcollection must also contain every scalar multiple of <m>\uvec{v}</m>. In particular, the subcollection must contain <m>0\uvec{v} = \zerovec</m>, as desired.
	</p>
	<aside><title>See</title><p>
	<xref ref="proposition-abstract-vec-spaces-basic-vec-props-zero-scalar-mul">Rule</xref>
	of
	<xref ref="proposition-abstract-vec-spaces-basic-vec-props" />
	</p></aside>
	<p>
	To show that the subcollection must be closed under taking negatives, consider a vector <m>\uvec{w}</m> in the subcollection. Again,
	<xref ref="proposition-subspaces-test-nonempty">Condition</xref>
	of the test says that the subcollection must also contain every scalar multiple of <m>\uvec{w}</m>. In particular, the subcollection must contain <m>(-1)\uvec{w} = -\uvec{w}</m>, as desired.
	</p>
	<aside><title>See</title><p>
	<xref ref="proposition-abstract-vec-spaces-basic-vec-props-neg-scalar-mul">Rule</xref>
	of
	<xref ref="proposition-abstract-vec-spaces-basic-vec-props" />
	</p></aside>
	<p>
	Finally, we will consider the <q>only if</q> part of the statement. Suppose we have a subcollection of vectors in a vector space that we already know is a subspace. A subspace is itself a vector space, so it must be nonempty (since it at least contains <em>some</em> zero vector by
	<xref ref="list-abstract-vec-spaces-concepts-add-axioms-zero" text="local">Axiom A</xref>),
	it must be closed under vector addition
	(<xref ref="list-abstract-vec-spaces-concepts-add-axioms-closed" text="local">Axiom A</xref>),
	and it must be closed under scalar multiplication
	(<xref ref="list-abstract-vec-spaces-concepts-smul-axioms-closed" text="local">Axiom S</xref>).
	In other words, it must pass the Subspace Test.
	</p></proof>

</proposition>

<p>
As per the proposition above, every subspace satisfies the statements of the Subspace Test. But we can go a little further.
</p>

<proposition xml:id="proposition-subspaces-props">

	<title>Properties of subspaces</title>

	<statement><p>
	Every subspace of a vector space contains the zero vector of that space, and is closed under vector addition, scalar multiplication, taking negatives, and taking linear combinations.
	</p></statement>

	<proof><p>
	We have already established that a subspace is closed under the vector operations. Verifying that it also contains the zero vector and is closed under taking negatives is exactly as in the proof of <xref ref="proposition-subspaces-test" /> above, since we know that a subspace always passes the Subspace Test.
	</p><p>
	It remains to show that a subspace is closed under linear combinations. So suppose that
	<m>\uvec{v}_1,\uvec{v}_2,\dotsc,\uvec{v}_\ell</m>
	are vectors in the subspace. Since the subspace is closed under scalar multiplication, the vectors
	<m>k_1\uvec{v}_1,k_2\uvec{v}_2,\dotsc,k_\ell\uvec{v}_\ell</m>
	are all also in the subspace. And then, since the subspace is also closed under addition, the linear combination
	<m>k_1\uvec{v}_1 + k_2\uvec{v}_2 + \dotsb + k_\ell\uvec{v}_\ell</m>
	is also in the subspace.
	</p></proof>

</proposition>

<p>
From the first property of subspaces listed above, we can deduce our observation about the best way to verify
<xref ref="proposition-subspaces-test-nonempty">Condition</xref> of the Subspace Test.
</p>

<corollary>
	<title> Subspaces must contain the zero vector </title>
	<statement><p>
	If a subcollection of a vector space does <em>not</em> contain the zero vector of the larger space, then it cannot be a subspace.
	</p></statement>
</corollary>

</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="subsection-subspaces-theory-examples">
<title>Universal examples of subspaces</title>

<p> Here we recognize examples of subspaces that occur in every vector space. </p>

<proposition xml:id="proposition-subspaces-trivial-and-full">
	<title>The trivial and full subspaces</title>
	<statement><p>
	In every vector space, both the zero space <m>\{\zerovec\}</m> and the whole space are subspaces.
	</p></statement>
	<proof><p>
	We verified these examples of subspaces in
	<xref ref="example-subspaces-examples-trivial-subspace" />
	and
	<xref ref="example-subspaces-examples-full-subspace" />
	of
	<xref ref="subsection-subspaces-examples-important" />.
	</p></proof>
</proposition>

<proposition xml:id="proposition-subspaces-span-subspace">

	<title>Creating subspaces via spanning sets</title>

	<statement><p><ol>
		<li xml:id="proposition-subspaces-span-subspace-is-subspace">
		If <m>S</m> is a nonempty collection of vectors in a vector space, then <m>\Span S</m> is a subspace of that vector space, and it contains every vector in <m>S</m>.
		</li>
		<li xml:id="proposition-subspaces-span-subspace-is-smallest">
		The subspace <m>\Span S</m> is the <em>smallest</em> subspace that contains every vector in <m>S</m> in the following sense: every other subspace that contains the vectors of <m>S</m> must also contain <m>\Span S</m> as a subspace.
		</li>
		<li xml:id="proposition-subspaces-span-subspace-full">
		<!-- used to be its own proposition, labelled: \labelprop{every.space.is.spanned} -->
		Every vector space (and hence, every subspace of a vector space) has a spanning set.
		</li>
	</ol></p></statement>

	<proof><p><ol>

		<li>
			<p>
			Recall that <m>\Span S</m> is the collection of all possible linear combinations of vectors in <m>S</m>. First we verify that <m>\Span S</m> contains every vector in <m>S</m>. Indeed, if <m>\uvec{v}</m> is a vector in <m>S</m>, then it is trivially a linear combination of vectors in <m>S</m> by <m>\uvec{v} = 1\uvec{v}</m>.
			</p><p>
			Let <m>V</m> represent the vector space from which the collection of vectors <m>S</m> is taken. First, we know that every vector in <m>\Span S</m> is a vector in <m>V</m>, because the vectors in <m>\Span S</m> are linear combinations of the vectors in <m>S</m>, and <m>V</m> is closed under taking linear combinations (<xref ref="proposition-subspaces-props" />, where <m>V</m> is considered as a subspace of itself using
			<xref ref="proposition-subspaces-trivial-and-full"/>). So <m>\Span S</m> is a subcollection of <m>V</m>.
			</p><p>
			Now let's apply the Subspace Test to <m>\Span S</m>.
			</p>
			<case><title><xref ref="proposition-subspaces-test-nonempty">Condition</xref></title><p>
				We know <m>\Span S</m> is nonempty because it contains each of the vectors of <m>S</m>.
			</p></case>
			<case><title><xref ref="proposition-subspaces-test-add-closed">Condition</xref></title><p>
				Suppose <m>\uvec{u}</m> and <m>\uvec{v}</m> are vectors in <m>\Span S</m>. Then each is a linear combination of vectors in <m>S</m>, say
				<md>
					<mrow> \uvec{u} \amp= k_1\uvec{u}_1 + k_2\uvec{u}_2 + \dotsb + k_s\uvec{u}_s, </mrow>
					<mrow> \uvec{v} \amp= m_1\uvec{v}_1 + m_2\uvec{v}_2 + \dotsb + m_t\uvec{v}_t, </mrow>
				</md>
				where each of <m>\uvec{u}_1,\uvec{u}_2,\dotsc,\uvec{u}_s</m> and <m>\uvec{v}_1,\uvec{v}_2,\dotsc,\uvec{v}_t</m> are vectors in <m>S</m>. Then,
				<md>
					<mrow> \uvec{u} + \uvec{v} \amp = k_1\uvec{u}_1 + k_2\uvec{u}_2 + \dotsb + k_s\uvec{u}_s </mrow>
					<mrow> \amp\phantom{=} \quad {} + m_1\uvec{v}_1 + m_2\uvec{v}_2 + \dotsb + m_t\uvec{v}_t, </mrow>
				</md>
				which is again a linear combination of vectors in <m>S</m>, so <m>\uvec{u}+\uvec{v}</m> is also in <m>\Span S</m>. This shows that <m>\Span S</m> is closed under vector addition.
			</p></case>
			<case><title><xref ref="proposition-subspaces-test-smul-closed">Condition</xref></title><p>
				Suppose <m>\uvec{v}</m> is a vector in <m>\Span S</m>. Then it is a linear combination of vectors in <m>S</m>, say
				<me> \uvec{v} = m_1\uvec{v}_1 + m_2\uvec{v}_2 + \dotsb + m_\ell\uvec{v}_\ell, </me>
				where each of <m>\uvec{v}_1,\uvec{v}_2,\dotsc,\uvec{v}_\ell</m> are vectors in <m>S</m>. Then for every scalar <m>k</m>,
				<md>
					<mrow> k\uvec{v} \amp = k(m_1\uvec{v}_1 + m_2\uvec{v}_2 + \dotsb + m_t\uvec{v}_\ell) </mrow>
					<mrow> \amp = km_1\uvec{v}_1 + km_2\uvec{v}_2 + \dotsb + km_\ell\uvec{v}_\ell, </mrow>
				</md>
				which is again a linear combination of vectors in <m>S</m>, so <m>k\uvec{v}</m> is always also in <m>\Span S</m>. This shows that <m>\Span S</m> is closed under scalar multiplication.
			</p></case>
			<p>
			Since <m>\Span S</m> passes the Subspace Test, it is a subspace of <m>V</m>.
			</p>
		</li>

		<li>
			<p>
			We wish to show that every other subspace that contains the vectors of <m>S</m> must also contain <m>\Span S</m> as a subspace. So suppose we have another subspace that contains the vectors of <m>S</m>. Then it must contain every linear combination of the vectors in <m>S</m>, since subspaces are closed under taking linear combinations (<xref ref="proposition-subspaces-props" />). That is, if a subspace contains all of the vectors in <m>S</m>, then it must also contain all of the vectors in <m>\Span S</m>.
			</p>
			<aside><title>Note</title><p>
				There is no need to use the Subspace Test to prove that <m>\Span S</m> is a subspace of this other subspace <mdash /> we already know from <xref ref="proposition-subspaces-span-subspace-is-subspace">Statement</xref> that <m>\Span S</m> is a subspace of <m>V</m>, the vector space from which the vectors <m>S</m> are taken. So <m>\Span S</m> is a vector space all on its own, hence will be a subspace of <em>any</em> space that contains all of its vectors. (See the definition of <term>subspace</term> in <xref ref="section-subspaces-terminology" />.)
			</p></aside>
		</li>

		<li>
			A vector space <m>V</m> always has an obvious spanning set <mdash /> itself! That is, we claim that <m>V = \Span V</m> is always true. To verify this, we must demonstrate that each vector in the collection <m>V</m> is also in the collection <m>\Span V</m>, and vice versa, so that they are exactly the same collection of vectors. However, by applying
			<xref ref="proposition-subspaces-span-subspace-is-subspace">Statement</xref> we can immediately say that <m>\Span V</m> is a subspace of <m>V</m> (implying every vector in <m>\Span V</m> is in <m>V</m>) that contains every vector of the spanning set <m>V</m> (<ie /> every vector in <m>V</m> is in <m>\Span V</m>).
		</li>

	</ol></p></proof>

</proposition>

</subsection>


<subsection xml:id="subsection-subspaces-theory-equality">
<title>Equality of subspaces created via spanning sets</title>

<p>Finally, we provide a way to determine when two spanning sets generate the same subspace.</p>

<proposition xml:id="proposition-subspaces-eq-span-test">

	<title> Comparing spanned spaces </title>

	<statement><p>
	Suppose <m>S</m> and <m>S'</m> are two sets of vectors in a vector space.
	<ol>
		<li xml:id="proposition-subspaces-eq-span-test-first-step">
		If each vector in <m>S</m> can be expressed as a linear combination of the vectors in <m>S'</m>, then <m>\Span S</m> is a subspace of <m>\Span S'</m>.
		</li>
		<li xml:id="proposition-subspaces-eq-span-test-eq-test">
		If each vector in <m>S</m> can be expressed as a linear combination of the vectors in <m>S'</m>, <em>and</em> each vector in <m>S'</m> can be expressed as a linear combination of the vectors in <m>S</m>, then <m>\Span S</m> and <m>\Span S'</m> are the same space.
		</li>
	</ol>
	</p></statement>

	<proof><p><ol>
		<li> Recall that <m>\Span S'</m> is the collection of all possible linear combinations of the vectors in <m>S'</m>. So assuming that each vector in <m>S</m> can be expressed as a linear combination of the vectors in <m>S'</m> is the same as assuming that each vector in <m>S</m> is in <m>\Span S'</m>. But
		<xref ref="proposition-subspaces-span-subspace-is-smallest">Statement</xref>
		of
		<xref ref="proposition-subspaces-span-subspace" />
		tells us that <m>\Span S</m> is the <em>smallest</em> subspace that contains all the vectors in <m>S</m>, and that <m>\Span S</m> must therefore be a subspace of <m>\Span S'</m>.
		</li>
		<li> Now we assume both that each vector in <m>S</m> can be expressed as a linear combination of the vectors in <m>S'</m> and that each vector in <m>S'</m> can be expressed as a linear combination of the vectors in <m>S</m>. Then we can apply <xref ref="proposition-subspaces-eq-span-test-first-step">Statement</xref> of this proposition twice, first to conclude that <m>\Span S</m> is a subspace of <m>\Span S'</m>, and second to conclude that <m>\Span S'</m> is a subspace of <m>\Span S</m>. But then <m>\Span S</m> is a subcollection of the vectors in <m>\Span S'</m>, and also vice versa. This can only happen if they are in fact the same collection of vectors.
		</li>
	</ol></p></proof>

</proposition>

</subsection>

</section>
