<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
© 2016–2018 Jeremy Sylvestre

Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or
any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled “GNU Free
Documentation License” that appears in the output document of this
PreTeXt source code. All trademarks™ are the registered® marks of their
respective owners.
*********************************************************************-->


<section xml:id="section-row-red-activities">

<title>Activities</title>

<assemblage><title>Reminder</title>
<p>
The elementary row operations are
<ol label="(i)">
	<li>swap rows;</li>
	<li>multiply a row by a non-zero constant; and</li>
	<li>add a multiple of one row to another.</li>
</ol></p>
</assemblage>

<activity xml:id="activity-row-red-system-unique-sol">
	<introduction><p>
		Consider the following system.
		<me>
			\left\{\begin{array}{rcrcrcr}
				2x \amp \amp \amp - \amp 2z \amp = \amp 3, \\
				x \amp - \amp y \amp \amp \amp = \amp 2,\\
				4x \amp - \amp 2y \amp - \amp 3z \amp = \amp 7.
			\end{array}\right.
		</me>
	</p></introduction>
	<task><p> Convert to an augmented matrix. </p></task>
	<task><p>
		Via elementary row operations, obtain a <q>leading <m>1</m></q> in the first entry of the first row (maybe swap some rows?), then use it to eliminate all other entries in the first column.
	</p></task>
	<task><p>
		Obtain a leading <m>1</m> in the second entry of the second row (do not use/alter the first row!), then use it to eliminate all other entries in the second column (yes, you can now alter the first row).
	</p></task>
	<task><p>
		Obtain a leading <m>1</m> in the third entry of the third row (do not use/alter first or second rows!), then use it to eliminate all other entries in the third column.
	</p></task>
	<task><p> Turn the final augmented matrix back into a system and solve it. </p></task>
</activity>

<activity xml:id="activity-row-red-system-infinite-sol">
	<introduction><p>
		Consider the following system.
		<me>
			\left\{\begin{array}{rcrcrcr}
				3x \amp + \amp 6y \amp + \amp 5z \amp = \amp -9,\\
				2x \amp + \amp 4y \amp + \amp 3z \amp = \amp -5,\\
				3x \amp + \amp 6y \amp + \amp 6z \amp = \amp -12.
			\end{array}\right.
		</me>
	</p></introduction>
	<task><p> Convert to an augmented matrix. </p></task>
	<task><p>
		Via elementary row operations, obtain a leading <m>1</m> in the first entry of the first row (maybe combine first two rows somehow?), then use it to eliminate all other entries in the first column.
	</p></task>
	<task><p> Is it possible to obtain a leading <m>1</m> in the second entry of the second row? </p></task>
	<task><p>
		Obtain a leading <m>1</m> in third entry of the second row (do not use/alter the first row!), then use it to eliminate all other entries in the third column.
	</p></task>
	<task><p>
		Assign a parameter to any variable whose column \emph{does not} contain a leading one. Turn the final augmented matrix back into a system and solve it in terms of your parameter(s).
	</p></task>
</activity>

<activity xml:id="activity-row-red-system-no-sol">
	<introduction><p>
		Consider the following system.
		<me>
			\left\{\begin{array}{rcrcrcr}
				x \amp + \amp 2y \amp + \amp z \amp = \amp 2,\\
				2x \amp + \amp 5y \amp + \amp 2z \amp = \amp -3,\\
				2x \amp + \amp 4y \amp + \amp 2z \amp = \amp -1.
			\end{array}\right.
		</me>
	</p></introduction>
	<task><p> Convert to an augmented matrix. </p></task>
	<task><p>
		Use the leading <m>1</m> in first entry of the first row to eliminate all other entries in the first column.
	</p></task>
	<task><p>
		Convert the new third row back into an equation. What does this mean about the system?
	</p></task>
</activity>

<activity xml:id="activity-row-red-system-homog-sol">
	<introduction>
		<p>
		Consider the following system. Notice that the <q>equals</q> column is all zeros. Such a system is called <term>homogeneous</term>.
		<idx><h>homogeneous system</h></idx>
		<idx><h>system</h><h>homogeneous</h></idx>
		<me>
			\left\{\begin{array}{rcrcrcrcrcr}
				3x_1 \amp + \amp 6x_2 \amp - \amp 8x_3 \amp + \amp 13x_4 \amp = \amp 0,\\
				x_1 \amp + \amp 2x_2 \amp - \amp 2x_3 \amp + \amp 3x_4 \amp = \amp 0,\\
				2x_1 \amp + \amp 4x_2 \amp - \amp 5x_3 \amp + \amp 8x_4 \amp = \amp 0.
			\end{array}\right.
		</me></p>
		<aside><title>Careful</title><p>
			After you've reduced the homogeneous system in this activity, remember that there is still the omitted <q>equals</q> column of all zeros.
		</p></aside>
	</introduction>
	<task><p> There is one obvious particular solution to the system. What is it? </p></task>
	<task><p> Will any row operation ever alter the <q>equals</q> column? </p></task>
	<task><p>
		Convert the system to a <term>coefficient matrix</term> (<ie /> omit the <q>equals</q> column). Then solve as usual.
	</p></task>
</activity>

<activity><p>
	In a homogeneous system, what is the relationship between the number of variables, the number of <q>leading ones</q> in the most reduced form of the coefficient matrix, and the number of parameters required to solve the system? What pattern of leading ones in a completely reduced coefficient matrix tells you that the corresponding homogeneous system has a single, unique solution?
</p></activity>

<activity><p>
	Consider system
	<me>
		\left\{\begin{array}{rcrcrcrcrcr}
			3x_1 \amp - \amp x_2 \amp + \amp 4x_3 \amp = \amp b_1,\\
			x_1 \amp + \amp 2x_2 \amp - \amp x_3 \amp = \amp b_2,\\
			3x_1 \amp \amp \amp + \amp 3x_3 \amp = \amp b_3,
		\end{array}\right.
	</me>
	where the constants of each equation are not specified. For what values of the unknown constants <m>b_1,b_2,b_3</m> is this system consistent?
	</p><p>
	To answer this question, row reduce the associated augmented matrix (below) until you are at a point where you can determine conditions on the constants <m>b_1,b_2,b_3</m> that ensures the system is consistent.
	<me>
		\left[\begin{array}{rrr|r}
			3 \amp -1 \amp 4 \amp b_1\\1 \amp 2 \amp -1 \amp b_2\\3 \amp 0 \amp 3 \amp b_3
		\end{array}\right].
	</me>
</p></activity>

</section>
