<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<section xml:id="section-applications-activities" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<title>Activities</title>

<introduction>
  <p>In this activity set, we look at some places where linear systems naturally arise.</p>
</introduction>

<activity xml:id="activity-applications-network">
  <statement>
  <p> Use the Law of Conservation (in this case, <em>flow in equals flow out</em> at each point of intersection) in the flow network below to set up a system of equations to determine the internal flow rates. (Do not solve your system.) </p>
  <p><image width="50%">
    <description>Flow network</description> <!-- description gets inserted as alt text in html img tag -->
    <latex-image><xi:include href="activity-tikz.d/flownet.tex" parse="text" /></latex-image>
  </image></p>
  </statement>
</activity>

<activity xml:id="activity-applications-chem-eq">
  <statement>
  <p>
  Set up a system of equations to balance the chemical equation:
  <me>a\mathrm{NH_3} + b\mathrm{O_2} \rightarrow c\mathrm{NO} + d\mathrm{H_2O}.</me>
  Do not solve your system.
  </p>
  <aside><p>
    You might have learned some procedure for balancing a chemical equation in high school. We are not interested in that procedure. We would like to see how attempting to balance a chemical equation has a linear system at its root.
  </p></aside>
  </statement>
</activity>

<activity xml:id="activity-applications-interpolate-line">
  <statement><p>
  Any two (distinct) points in the Cartesian plane determine a unique line. Set up a system of equations that would let you solve for the slope and <m>y</m>-intercept of the line <m>y=mx+b</m> that passes through the points <m>(-3,4)</m> and <m>(2,-1)</m> (but do not solve the system). Write down the augmented matrix for your system.
  </p></statement>
</activity>

<activity xml:id="activity-applications-interpolate-parabola">
  <statement><p>
  Any three (distinct, non-collinear) points in the Cartesian plane determine a unique parabola. Set up a system of equations that would let you solve for the coefficients <m>a,b,c</m> of the parabola <m>y=ax^2+bx+c</m> that passes through the points <m>(-1,-4)</m>, <m>(1,0)</m>, and <m>(2,5)</m> (but do not solve the system). Write down the augmented matrix for your system.
  </p></statement>
</activity>

<activity xml:id="activity-applications-interpolate-degree-n">
  <statement><p>
  Based on the previous two activities and their answers, how many points are necessary to determine a unique degree <m>n</m> polynomial <m>y=a_n x^n + a_{n-1} x^{n-1} + \dotsb + a_1 x + a_0</m>? If you knew such points
  <me>(x_1,y_1),(x_2,y_2),(x_3,y_3),\dotsc,</me>
  and you used these points to create a linear system to determine the coefficients of the polynomial, what would be the pattern in the rows of the resulting augmented matrix for the system?
  </p></statement>
</activity>

</section>
