<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
© 2016–2018 Jeremy Sylvestre

Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or
any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled “GNU Free
Documentation License” that appears in the output document of this
PreTeXt source code. All trademarks™ are the registered® marks of their
respective owners.
*********************************************************************-->


<section xml:id="section-diagonalization-motivation">

<title>Motivation</title>

<p>
Similar matrices are truly that <mdash /> <em>similar</em>.
While their entries contain different data,
everything else about them is essentially the same.
Similar matrices have the same rank, nullity, determinant, characteristic polynomial, and eigenvalues.
For each shared eigenvalue,
similar matrices have the same algebraic and geometric multiplicities.
And via a known transition matrix to <em>transition</em> spaces from one to the other,
similar matrices have <q>similar</q> column spaces, null spaces, and eigenspaces.
When matrices are similar,
one can essentially be replaced by the other in computations,
and the transition matrix can be used to transition important vectors in those computations between the two matrices.
<!-- TODO: after extending material, insert a "look ahead" aside here -->
</p><p>
The simplest matrices with which to do computations are scalar matrices <mdash />
matrices that are equal to <m>kI</m> for some scalar <m>k</m>.
<aside> <title>See</title><p> <xref ref="chapter-special-forms" /> for a refresher on scalar matrices and their properties. </p> </aside>
But no matrix is similar to a scalar matrix,
other than the scalar matrix itself,
because for <m>A = kI</m> every possible transition matrix <m>P</m> would yield
<me> B = \inv{P}AP = \inv{P}(kI)P = k\inv{P}P = kI = A. </me>
</p>
<p>
So in this chapter we consider the next simplest type of matrix with which to do computations <mdash />
diagonal matrices.
</p>

<question><statement><p>
	When is a matrix similar to a diagonal matrix,
	and how do we determine a suitable transition matrix?
</p></statement></question>

<p>
We tackle this question by concentrating on the transition matrix <m>P</m>.
If <m>\inv{P}AP</m> is diagonal,
what relationships between <m>P</m>, <m>A</m>, and the diagonal matrix
<m>D=\inv{P}AP</m>
can we discover to help us understand this situation?
We have already answered these questions in
<xref ref="worksheet-diagonalization-activities" />.
In the next section we summarize our findings.
</p>

</section>
