<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
© 2016–2020 Jeremy Sylvestre

Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or
any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled “GNU Free
Documentation License” that appears in the output document of this
PreTeXt source code. All trademarks™ are the registered® marks of their
respective owners.
*********************************************************************-->


<section xml:id="section-abstract-vec-spaces-motivation" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<title>Motivation</title>

<p>
The rules of vector algebra listed in
<xref ref="proposition-vectors-Rn-algebra-rules" />
are valid whether we take a geometric view
(using directed line segments)
or an an algebraic view
(using column vectors)
of vector addition and scalar multiplication.
But all these rules have counterparts in matrix algebra in <xref ref="proposition-matrix-ops-algebra-rules" />,
which suggests that these algebra patterns might be more universal <mdash />
are there other collections of algebraic objects that can be added and scaled and that follow the same rules of algebra when we do so?
</p><p>
If we can find similar algebra patterns elsewhere (and we will),
then it is worth the effort to <em>abstract</em> the concepts of vector and vector algebra <mdash />
to disassociate them from any specific ideas of what they are,
and deal with them as abstract concepts.
This is ultimately where mathematics becomes most powerful:
when it recognizes, describes, and analyzes patterns in familiar contexts that can then be recognized and exploited in new contexts.
</p><p>
The cycle of life of a mathematical idea is as follows.
<ul>
	<li>
		Extract common patterns from familiar <em>model</em> systems
		(on the left in
		<xref ref="figure-abstract-vec-spaces-motivation-math-models" />
		below).
	</li>
	<li> Describe the core features of these common patterns and use them as the basis for an abstract system. </li>
	<li> Deduce new properties of the abstract system based on the aspects of the underlying patterns that describe it. </li>
	<li>
		Recognize the common patterns described by the abstract system in new systems
		(on the right in
		<xref ref="figure-abstract-vec-spaces-motivation-math-models" />
		below).
	</li>
	<li> Interpret the new abstract properties back in the known systems, new and old, and apply these properties to solve problems. </li>
</ul>
Since the abstract properties are logically deduced from the underlying patterns that defines the abstract system,
every specific system that follows these common patterns must have the same properties.
</p>

<figure xml:id="figure-abstract-vec-spaces-motivation-math-models">
	<caption>The cycle of abstract mathematical models.</caption>
	<image width="100%">
		<!-- description gets inserted as alt text in html img tag -->
		<description>The cycle of abstract modelling.</description>
		<latex-image><xi:include href="motivation.d/modelling.tex" parse="text" /></latex-image>
	</image>
</figure>

<p>
Following this cycle for systems that follow the patterns of the rules of algebra for
<term>vector addition</term> and <term>scalar multiplication</term>
is our task for the next few chapters.
In this chapter, we begin our study of the abstract system we can extract from our familiar model systems of vectors in <m>\R^n</m> and <m>m \times n</m> matrices,
both of which satisfy the same rules of algebra with respect to addition and scalar multiplication.
</p>

</section>
