<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<frontmatter xml:id="index" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

  <titlepage>

    <author>
      <personname>Jeremy Sylvestre</personname>
      <department>Augustana Faculty</department>
      <institution>University of Alberta</institution>
      <email>jeremy.sylvestre@ualberta.ca</email>
    </author>

    <date><today /></date>

  </titlepage>

  <colophon xml:id="front-colophon">

    <edition>PreTeXt Edition 2018</edition>

    <website>
      <name>Discover Linear Algebra</name>
      <address>https://sites.ualberta.ca/~jsylvest/books/DLA/</address>
    </website>

    <website>
      <name>GitHub source code repository</name>
      <address>https://github.com/jjrsylvestre/dla/</address>
    </website>

    <copyright>
      <year>2016<ndash />2018</year>
      <holder>Jeremy Sylvestre</holder>
      <minilicense>GFDL License</minilicense>
      <shortlicense>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.  A copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled <q>GNU Free Documentation License.</q>  All trademarks<trademark /> are the registered<registered /> marks of their respective owners.</shortlicense>
    </copyright>

  </colophon>

  <biography xml:id="author-bio-JS">
    <p>
    Jeremy Sylvestre is Associate Professor of Mathematics at the University of Alberta's Augustana Campus.
    <!-- TODO could be a little more verbose ... ;) -->
    </p>
  </biography>

  <preface xml:id="preface">

    <p> The purpose of this book is to serve as supporting material for a fairly typical course in <em>Linear Algebra</em> using a discovery-based pedagogical approach. </p>

    <p>
    Each chapter is organized into sections titled <em>Activities</em>, <em>Terminology and notation</em>, <em>Concepts</em>, <em>Examples</em>, and <em>Theory</em> (though some chapters have additional <em>Motivation</em> and/or <em>More examples</em> sections).
    </p><p>
    The purpose for employing this uniform sectioning scheme is to give the student a uniform flow to encountering each new collection of topics:
    <dl>
      <li><title><em>Activities</em></title>
      <p> initial encounter through discovery- and problem-solving-based activities; </p>
      </li>
      <li><title><em>Terminology and notation</em></title>
      <p> introduction of the communication tools necessary to begin a more sophisticated conversation about the new topics; </p>
      </li>
      <li><title><em>Concepts</em></title>
      <p> fuller discussion of the new topics, grounded in reflections on the questions and results of the <em>Activities</em> section; </p>
      </li>
      <li><title><em>Examples</em></title>
      <p> computational examples to assist students with the procedural tasks related to the new topics, as well as additional examples that serve to illustrate certain concepts; and </p>
      </li>
      <li><title><em>Theory</em></title>
      <p> a more formal and general description of the concepts, with proofs. </p>
      </li>
    </dl>
    Traditional textbooks usually intersperse terminology, concepts, examples, and theory in a linear narrative, and relegate <q>activities</q> to the <em>Exercises</em> section at the end of the chapter. By organizing the flow of learning in the above-described manner, it is hoped that the process of encountering and re-encountering (and <em>re</em>-encountering) the topics in different modes <mdash /> discovery, reflection and discussion, examples, and theory <mdash /> and at increasing levels of sophistication will lead to deeper learning.
    </p>

    <!-- TODO more ...? -->

    <attribution>
      <line>Jeremy Sylvestre</line>
      <line>Camrose, Alberta 2018</line>
    </attribution>

  </preface>

</frontmatter>
