<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
© 2016–2018 Jeremy Sylvestre

Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or
any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled “GNU Free
Documentation License” that appears in the output document of this
PreTeXt source code. All trademarks™ are the registered® marks of their
respective owners.
*********************************************************************-->

<!-- TODO index-ify this -->

<appendix xml:id="appendix-complex">

<title>Complex numbers</title>

<section>
<title>Motivation</title>

<p>We begin with a few examples.</p>

<example><statement><p><ul>
  <li> The polynomial equation <m>x^4 - 5x^2 + 4 = 0</m> has four solutions: <m>x = 1</m>, <m>x = -1</m>, <m>x = 2</m>, and <m>x = -2</m>. </li>
  <li> The polynomial equation <m>x^4 - 1 = 0</m> has two solutions: <m>x = 1</m> and <m>x = -1</m>. </li>
  <li> The polynomial equation <m>x^4 + 1  = 0</m> has no solutions. </li>
</ul></p></statement></example>

<p> Solutions of a polynomial equation are called the <term>roots</term> of the equation, and are also often referred to as <term>roots</term> of the polynomial involved. From the examples above, different polynomials of the same degree can have different numbers of roots. </p>

<question><statement><p>
  What can we say about the possibilities for the number of roots a polynomial can have?
</p></statement></question>

<theorem xml:id="theorem-complex-fund-thm-alg">
  <title>The Fundamental Theorem of Algebra</title>
  <statement><p>
    If <m>p(x)</m> is a polynomial of degree <m>n \ge 1</m>, then the polynomial equation <m>p(x) = 0</m> has <emph>at most</emph> <m>n</m> roots, even when repeated roots are counted multiple times, according to the number of times that root is repeated.
  </p></statement>
  <proof><title>Proof idea</title><p>
    A proper proof would use proof by induction, but we will be a little less formal. If the polynomial equation <m>p(x) = 0</m> has no solutions at all, then clearly the number of solutions is not more than the degree <m>n</m>. On the other hand, if this equation has distinct solutions <m>x_1,x_2,\dotsc,x_\ell</m>, then it is a fact of algebra that we can factor <m>p(x)</m> as
    <me> p(x) = (x-x_1)^{m_1} (x-x_1)^{m_2} \dotsm (x-x_\ell)^{m_\ell} q(x), </me>
    where each exponent <m>m_i</m> is equal to the number of times solution <m>x=x_i</m> is repeated as a root of the equation (called the <term>multiplicity</term> of the root), and <m>q(x)</m> is another polynomial with no roots.
  </p><p>
    Since the degree of the factorization of <m>p(x)</m> above must be the same as the degree of <m>p(x)</m>, the sum <m>m_1 + m_2 + \dotsb + m_\ell</m> cannot be greater than <m>n</m>, and this sum of multiplicities is exactly the number of roots of the equation <m>p(x)=0</m> (including repetition).
  </p></proof>
</theorem>

<p> In some sense, the <em>optimal</em> situation is when a polynomial has a full slate of roots (including repetition), so that the polynomial can be fully factored into linear terms. In order to <q>fix</q> the problem of some polynomials having fewer than a full slate of roots, we will just <q>invent</q> solutions for these root-deficient polynomials. </p>

<p> The quintessential example of a polynomial equation with no solution is <m> x^2 + 1 = 0 </m>. Let's start by inventing a solution to this equation. </p>

<definition>
  <title>The imaginary number <m>\ci</m></title>
  <statement><p> An imaginary <q>number</q> that satisfies <m>\ci^2 + 1 = 0</m>. </p></statement>
</definition>

<note><p>
Notice in particular that <m>\ci^2 = -1</m>, which will be the main way that we use the definition of <m>\ci</m> above in algebraic computations.
</p></note>

<remark><p>
It is common to think of <m>\ci</m> as being equal to <m>\sqrt{-1}</m>, because
<me> (\sqrt{-1})^2 + 1 = -1 + 1 = 0 </me>
suggests that if <m>-1</m> had a square root, then it would be a solution to <m>x^2+1=0</m>, which is what's desired. However, the notation <m>\sqrt{-1}</m> implies that this is a <emph>positive</emph> square root, <ie /> greater than zero. Where we're going, concepts of <q>greater than</q> and <q>less than</q> will no longer be meaningful.
</p></remark>

<p>
If we want to treat this new imaginary number just like our ordinary real numbers that we're used to, we would like to be able to perform operations invovling it and other numbers, such as addition, subtraction, multiplication, division, and taking negatives. To do this, we will treat <m>\ci</m> algebraically as if it were a variable.
</p>

<p>
More on that in the next section. For now, let's just start with taking negatives. Since <m>(-x)^2 = x^2</m> for every real number <m>x</m>, we will require the same of our new imaginary number: <m>(-\ci)^2 = \ci^2</m>. But then
aSo if we stipulate that <m>-\ci</m> is not the same imaginary number as <m>\ci</m> (a reasonable requirement, since no nonzero real number is equal to its own negative), then with the invention of the imaginary number <m>\ci</m>, the polynomial equation <m>x^2 + 1 = 0</m> now has just as many solutions as the degree of the polynomial involved! </p>

<p>In summary, in the example of the polynomial <m>x^2 + 1</m>, we can go from having no solutions to the full amount allowed by <xref ref="theorem-complex-fund-thm-alg" text="title" /> by inventing one solution.</p>

</section>

<section>
<title>The field of complex numbers</title>
<!-- TODO probably needs subsectioning -->

<p> Now that we have a new number, let's let it out to play with all the other numbers. </p>

<example><statement><p>
  Suppose we have polynomial <m>x^2 - 6x + 13</m>. Is the <q>number</q> <m>3+2\ci</m> a root?
  <md>
    <mrow>
      (3+2\ci)^2 - 6(3+2\ci) + b
      \amp = (9 + 12\ci + 4(-1)) - 18 - 12\ci + 13
      \amp \amp (\ci^2 = -1)
    </mrow>
    <mrow>
      \amp = 0.
    </mrow>
  </md>
  The answer is yes! By algebraically combining <m>\ci</m>, which is a root of the prototypical <q>unsolvable</q> polynomial equation <m>x^2+1</m>, with other real numbers, we obtain roots of other previously  <q>unsolvable</q> polynomial equations.
</p></statement></example>

<p> It turns out that the result of combining such expressions involving <m>\ci</m> using the four operations of addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division can always be simplified using <m>i^2 = -1 </m> down to something of the form <m>a + b\ci</m>, where <m>a,b</m> are real numbers. </p>

<definition><title>The field of complex numbers</title><statement><p>
  The collection <m>\C</m> of all possible algebraic expressions <m>a+b\ci</m>, where <m>a,b</m> are real numbers. Expressions of this form are called <term>complex numbers</term>. In such an expression, the number <m>a</m> is called the <term>real part</term> and the number <m>b</m> is called the <term>imaginary part</term>.
</p></statement></definition>

<example><title>Real and imaginary parts</title><statement><p><ul>
  <li> The complex number <m>-3+\frac{1}{2}\ci</m> has real part <m>-3</m> and imaginary part <m>\frac{1}{2}</m>. </li>
  <li> The complex number <m>e - \pi\ci = e + (-\pi)\ci</m> has real part <m>e</m> and imaginary part <m>-\pi</m>. </li>
</ul></p></statement></example>

<p> Here are examples of adding, subtracting, multiplying, and exponentiating complex numbers. (We will deal with division afterward.) Notice it mostly involves just familiar algebra: collecting like terms and FOIL. </p>

<example><title>Algebraic operations involving complex numbers</title>
  <statement><p><ol>
    <li> <m>(3+\ci) + (5-3\ci) = 8 - 2\ci</m>. </li>
    <li> <m>(3+\ci) - (5-3\ci) = -2 + 4\ci</m>. </li>
    <li> <m>(3+\ci)(5-3\ci) = 15 - 4\ci - 3(-1) = 18 - 4\ci </m>. </li>
    <li> <m>(3+\ci)^2 = 9 + 6\ci + (-1) = 8 + 6\ci </m>. </li>
    <li> <m>(5-3\ci)(5+3\ci) = 25 + 0\ci - 9(-1) = 34 </m>. </li>
  </ol></p></statement>
</example>

<p> The last in the list of examples above is particularly important. You may recognize it as related to the factorization of a difference of squares. Since <m>\ci^2 = -1</m>, multiplying a complex number against its <q>difference-of-squares-factorization partner</q> like this always results in a real number. Because of this, we'll give this partner a name. </p>

<definition><title>Complex conjugate</title><statement><p>
  For complex number <m>z = a + b\ci</m>, we define the <term>complex conjugate</term> of <m>z</m> to be
  <me> \cconj{z} = \lcconj{a+b\ci} = a - \b\ci. </me>
</p></statement></definition>

<remark><p>
You should think of complex conjugate as <q>flipping the sign</q> on the imaginary part of the complex number. In particular, if <m>z = a - b\ci</m>, then <m>\cconj{z} = \lcconj{a - b\ci} = a + b\ci</m>.
</p></remark>

<example><title>Computing complex conjgates</title><statement><p>
  <ul>
  <li><m>\lccong{5+4\ci} = 5 - 4\ci</m>.</li>
  <li><m>\lccong{e-\pi\ci} = e + \pi\ci</m>.</li>
  </ul>
</p></statement></example>

<p> Before we list some properties of the complex conjugate, we will use it to help us divide complex numbers. </p>

<example><title>Division of complex numbers</title><statement><p>
  To simplify a ratio of complex numbers, we can use the conjugate to <emph>rationalize the denominator</emph>, as if <m>\ci</m> really was equal to <m>\sqrt{-1}</m>.
  <md>
    <mrow>
      \frac{3+4\ci}{2-3\ci}
      \amp =
    </mrow>
  </md>
</p></statement></example>

<proposition><title>Properties of complex conjugates</title><statement><p>
  The following are valid rules of algebra involving the complex conjugation operation involving complex numbers <m>w</m> and <m>z</m> and real number <m>k</m>.
  <ol>
    <li> <m>\cconj{k} = k</m>. </li>
    <li> <m>\lcconj{kz} = k\cconj{z}. </m> </li>
    <li> <m>\lcconj{w+z} = \cconj{w} + \cconj{z}. </m> </li>
    <li> <m>\lcconj{wz} = \cconj{w}\cconj{z}. </m> </li>
    <li>
  </ol>
</p></statement></proposition>

</section>

</appendix>
