<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
© 2016–2021 Jeremy Sylvestre

Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or
any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled “GNU Free
Documentation License” that appears in the output document of this
PreTeXt source code. All trademarks™ are the registered® marks of their
respective owners.
*********************************************************************-->


<section xml:id="section-elem-nilpotent-motivation" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<title>Motivation</title>

<p>
We continue on our quest to answer <xref ref="question-block-diag-motivation-similarity-class-reps" />.
If we are happy with triangular block form, then we have succeeded:
every matrix is similar (over <m>\C</m>) to one in triangular block form.
But could we make a triangular block form similar to some even simpler form?
</p>

<paragraphs><title>Philosophy of inquiry: break the problem apart</title><p>
	If a problem is made up of readily-identifiable smaller and/or simpler parts,
	concentrate on each individual part separately,
	if possible.
</p></paragraphs>

<p>
A matrix in triangular block form is immediately recognizable as being made out of parts that are both smaller and simpler:
the blocks themselves.
But we can break each block into parts as well.
</p><p>
Each block in triangular block form is in scalar-triangular form,
and a scalar-triangular form matrix can be decomposed as a sum
<me> \lambda I + N </me>
of a scalar matrix <m>\lambda I</m> and a nilpotent matrix <m>N</m>.
As we realized in <xref ref="activity-elem-nilpotent-moving-past-triang-block" />,
attempting to simplify each block in triangular form is equivalent to simplifying each nilpotent part of the scalar-triangular blocks.
However, just as we did when we considered scalar-triangular form as an initial special case before analyzing general triangular block form,
we will consider first consider a special case of nilpotent matrix.
</p>

<paragraphs><title>Philosophy of inquiry: analyze the <q>cusp</q> case</title>
	<p>
	A <q>cusp</q> is a boundary between two different kinds of behaviour,
	in analogy with a cusp point on the graph of a function.
	</p>
	<image width="50%">
	  <!-- description gets inserted as alt text in html img tag -->
	  <description> Visualization of a cusp point  </description>
	  <latex-image><xi:include href="motivation.d/cusp.tex" parse="text" /></latex-image>
	</image>
	<p> A cusp is often where interesting things happen or where special patterns are revealed. </p>
</paragraphs>

<p>
In <xref ref="chapter-eigen-values-vectors" />,
we learned that a singular matrix must have <m>\lambda = 0</m> as an eigenvalue
(<xref ref="theorem-eigen-values-vectors-equiv-to-invertible" />).
So in the triangular form for a singular matrix,
one of the blocks will have zeros down the diagonal,
with as many diagonal zeros as the algebraic multiplicity of eigenvalue <m>\lambda = 0</m> in the characteristic polynomial.
We often think of a singular matrix as being <q>like zero</q>,
since <m>0</m> is the only <em>number</em> that does not have an inverse.
But an <m>n \times n</m> zero matrix has eigenvalue <m>\lambda = 0</m> with <em>maximum</em> algebraic multiplicity <m>m_\lambda = n</m>.
So, in a way,
the algebraic multiplicity of <m>\lambda = 0</m> for a singular matrix measures how <q>close</q> to being zero that matrix is.
</p>
<figure>
	<caption>
		Partition of the set of <m>n \times n</m> matrices into invertible and singular,
		with the set of singular matrices further partitioned by multiplicity of the eigenvalue <m>\lambda = 0</m>.
	</caption>
	<image width="75%">
		<!-- description gets inserted as alt text in html img tag -->
		<description>Diagram of a partition of the set of <m>n \times n</m> matrices.</description>
		<latex-image><xi:include href="motivation.d/nxn-partition.tex" parse="text" /></latex-image>
	</image>
</figure>

<p>
But the zero matrix is not the sole example of a matrix with eigenvalue <m>\lambda = 0</m> of maximum algebraic multiplicity <mdash />
every nilpotent matrix does as well
(<xref ref="theorem-cayley-hamilton-characterizations-of-nilpotency-evalues">Statement</xref>
of <xref ref="theorem-cayley-hamilton-characterizations-of-nilpotency" />).
So in one sense, nonzero nilpotent is as close as you can get to being zero without actually being zero.
</p><p>
However, we can further partition the set of nilpotent matrices of a particular size by <term>degree of nilpotency</term> <mdash />
the lowest positive exponent which takes the nilpotent matrix to zero.
The zero matrix stands alone in this partition,
as it is the only matrix with degree of nilpotency equal to <m>1</m>
(since it already <em>is</em> zero).
</p>
<figure>
	<caption> Partition of the set of <m>n \times n</m> singular matrices by <term>degree of nilpotency</term>. </caption>
	<image width="100%">
		<!-- description gets inserted as alt text in html img tag -->
		<description>Diagram of a partition of the set of nilpotent <m>n \times n</m> matrices.</description>
		<latex-image><xi:include href="motivation.d/nilpotent-nxn-partition.tex" parse="text" /></latex-image>
	</image>
</figure>
<p>
The <q>cusp</q> case we will consider is at the top of this partition:
those nilpotent matrices with degree of nilpotency <m>n</m>.
These matrices are <q>close</q> to zero in the sense that they are nilpotent
(and so have eigenvalue <m>\lambda = 0</m> with maximum algebraic multiplicity).
But of all nilpotent matrices they are as far from zero as possible,
since it takes the maximum exponent <m>n</m> for them to reveal their nilpotency.
They are on the <em>cusp</em> between being nilpotent and being singular non-nilpotent.
</p><p>
We have already encountered a prototypical example of this sort of nilpotent matrix that is <q>on the cusp</q>:
the <term>elementary nilpotent form</term> matrices of <xref ref="activity-elem-nilpotent-first-encounter" />.
Our task in this chapter (that we have already begun in <xref ref="worksheet-elem-nilpotent" />)
is to determine the pattern of similarity that emerges when a nilpotent matrix is similar to an elementary nilpotent one.
</p>

</section>
